Preliminary Guide to the Walter H. Smith Collection of Beat Literature, 1950-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walter H. Smith Collection of Beat Literature 1950-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Walter H. (collector)
4.1 linear feet Extent: 225 Items
Walter H. Smith donated this collection of Beat Literature. The majority relates to the career and life of Allen Ginsberg, a founding member of the Beat Generation. Other writers represented include Anne Waldman, Diane di Prima, and Anselm Hollo. Accessions (2009-0113) and (2009-0130) (200 items; 3.5 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2003) include books, compilations, journals, magazines, and other publications with works by and about Allen Ginsberg. Also included are posters and broadsides advertising events, readings, or publications by Ginsberg; many of these are signed. Accession (2010-0098) (25 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1950-2009) includes writings and some correspondence from Diane di Prima, Anselm Hollo, and Anne Waldman; also includes some Allen Ginsberg materials. Accession (2011-0045) (27 items; 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1963-2007) includes pamphlets and publications by Gary Snyder.
RL.00095
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter H. Smith Collection of Beat Literature was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008, 2009, 2010, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Walter H. Smith donated this collection of Beat literature. The majority of the collection is by and about Allen Ginsberg, a poet and member of the Beat Generation.
Allen Ginsberg was born in Newark, New Jersey, and grew up in the New York area. He entered Columbia University in the 1940s, where he developed close friendships with men like Jack Kerouac and Neal Cassidy, who, with Ginsberg, were founding members of what became known as the Beat Generation. Ginsberg's most famous work, Howl and Other Poems, was published in 1956, and became a test case for fighting obscenity and censorship laws. He was also an outspoken proponent for gay rights, the legalization of marijuana and other drugs, and free speech, and frequently led protests against the Vietnam War during the 1960s and 1970s. He went on to publish numerous volumes and compilations of poetry, and later became a professor at Brooklyn College. He died in New York City at the age of 70. (Source: Academy of American Poets, www.poets.org)
Diane di Prima was born in 1934 and became an important writer and poet in the Beat movement. She has written over 40 books of poetry and prose, and has won numerous grants and awards, including an Award for Lifetime Achievement from the National Poetry Association in 1993. In 2009, she was named the Poet Laureate of San Francisco. (Source: dianediprima.com)
Anne Waldman was born in 1945, and also joined the East Coast poetry scene in the 1960s. She was a co-founder, with Allen Ginsberg and others, of the Jack Kerouac School of Disembodied Poets, at Naropa Institute in Boulder, Colorado. She remains there as a professor and director of the Naropa University Summer Writing Program.
Anselm Hollo, born in Finland in 1934, has lived in the United States since 1967. He is a poet and translator, and has published over 40 titles of poetry. He also teaches creative writing at Naropa University.
Born in 1930, Gary Snyder is a Pulitzer Prize winning poet, ecological activist, founder of the Ring of Bone Zendo, and member of the English Department faculty of U.C. Davis.
Collection Overview
Accessions (2009-0113) and (2009-0130) (200 items; 3.5 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2003) include books, compilations, journals, magazines, and other publications with works by and about Allen Ginsberg. Also included are posters and broadsides advertising events, readings, or publications by Ginsberg; many of these are signed.
Accession (2010-0098) (25 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1964-2009) includes publications and some correspondence from Beat Generation poets such as Anne Waldman, Diane di Prima, Anselm Hollo, and Allen Ginsberg. Includes signatures of Hollo and Waldman.
Accession (2011-0045) (27 items; 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1963-2007) includes publications, pamphlets, and posters featuring works and readings by Gary Snyder.
Subject Headings
Smith, Walter H. (collector); Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; Di Prima, Diane; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Hollo, Anselm; Beat generation; Beat generation in literature; American literature -- 20th century; Posters
Contents of Collection
- Allen Ginsberg: Publications and Periodicals, (2 boxes)
  Includes books, journals, magazines and other periodicals, and various other publications that include work by or about Allen Ginsberg. Several include Ginsberg's signature.
  Materials listed first are stacked loose in the box; folders contain small, thin, or fragile publications.
  - American Review, No. 16, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Countdown, No. 3, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Countdown, No. 2, 1970 (Box 1)
  - New American Review, No. 11, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Boss, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Little Caesar (Lita Hornick article on Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac School of Disembodied Poets at the Naropa Institute), No. 10, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Long Shot, Vol. 27, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Long Shot, Vol. 15, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Long Shot, Vol. 4, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Long Shot, 1982 (Box 1)
  - The Paris Review (Thomas Clark interview, signed on page 13), Vol. 10, No. 37, Spring 1966 (Box 1)
  - The Portable Lower East Side, Vol. 6, No. 1, 1989 (Box 1)
  - ppHOO (Bengali-English-French from India, memorial issue), 1998 (Box 1)
  - The Seventies (signed by Robert Bly), No. 1, Spring 1972 (Box 1)
  - San Jose Studies, Vol. XIX, No. 1, Fall 1993 (Box 1)
  - Stony Brook, Vol. 1, No. 2, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Zero, Vol. 2, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Birth, No. 3, 1960 (Box 1)
  - California Librarian, Oct. 1970 (Box 1)
  - The Cambridge Review (Includes poem and review of Howl; signed by Allen Ginsberg), Dec. 1956 (Box 1)
  - New Directions, No. 14, 1953 (Box 1)
  - The New York Quarterly (signed by Allen Ginsberg), No. 2, Spring 1970 (Box 1)
  - Mulch (Ginsberg on Kerouac), Vol. 2, No. 2, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Poetry, Vol. 12, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Intrepid, No. 11/12, 1969 (Box 1)
  - East Side Review, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Georgia Straight (Thomas Forcade letter about Ginsberg controversy in Canadian underground newspaper), Vol. 7, No. 303, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Magical Blend (David Brown and Rebecca McGlen interview), No. 38, 1993 (Box 1)
  - New Age (Peter Chowka interview; cover signed by Ginsberg), 1976 (Box 1)
  - The New Censorship, Vol. 5, No. 4, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Nexus (Ginsberg memorial issue), Vol. 32, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oui (article by biographer Michael Schumacher), Vol. 11, No. 6, June 1982 (Box 1)
  - Parapluie, No. 10, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Playboy, Vol. 15, No. 12, Dec. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Nomad (signed), No. 9, Summer 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Big Sky, No. 1, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Big Sky, No. 2, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Anthology of Underground Poetry, Section 9, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Columbia Review, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Third Rail, No. 8, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Third Rail, No. 7, 1985/1986 (Box 1)
  - Synapse 3, Jan. 1965 (Box 1)
  - So & So, Fall 1978 (Box 1)
  - Ramparts, Vol. 5, No. 5, Nov. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shambhala Sun, Vol. 2, No. 6, July 1994 (Box 1)
  - Shout! Vol. 2, No. 1, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Swank, Vol. 7, No. 6, Jan. 1961 (Box 1)
  - Writer's Digest (article by biographer Michael Schumacher), May 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Herschel Silverman, High on the Beats. Atom Mind, Vol. 4, No. 16, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Bastard Angel 1, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Evergreen Review, No. 42, Aug. 1966 (Box 1)
  - Evergreen Review, No. 40, April 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Milk Quarterly, No. 8, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Vinduet, No. 3, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Eclipse, 8/9, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Camera Austria (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - SF Weekly, Vol. XIII, No. 50, Jan. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Opus International, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Panjandrum (vinyl LP and portfolio of broadsides and artwork), Vol. 1, No. 1, 1972 (Box 2)
  - The Sunday Camera Magazine, Nov. 11, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Sunday Camera Magazine, June 12, 1987 (Box 2)
  - The Village Voice (Ginsberg memorial issue), Vol. XLII, No. 15, 1997 (Box 2)
  - The Bloomsburg Review (interview by Bill Trembley), Vol. 5, No. 9, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Bookforum (review by David Gates), Summer 2005 (Box 2)
  - East West Journal (Marilyn Webb article on early Naropa scene), May 1976 (Box 2)
  - The American Poetry Review, Vol. 23, No. 3, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rolling Stone, No. 761 (Ginsberg memorial issue), 1997 (Box 2)
  - Rolling Stone, No. 204, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Jim Moore interview with Allen Ginsberg, Hungry Mind Review, No. 30, 1994 (Box 2)
- Allen Ginsberg: Broadsides, Handbills, and Posters Series, (2 boxes) (Box 2)
  Posters and broadsides advertising events, readings, or publications by or about Allen Ginsberg.
  - The Beat Generation, Spring class, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - First Annual Ginsberg Poetry Festival, 2003 (Box 3)
  - New York Poets, German Publication, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Kerouac Conference and Participants, 1982 (Box 3)
  - A Celebration of Life, Boulder, CO, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Reading at Columbia with Burroughs, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Reading in Berkeley, CA, for Nyingmapa, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Reading with Diane Di Prima, Denver, CO, 1982 (Box 3)
  - San Francisco Oracle, Vol. 1, No. 7, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Promotional photograph by Robert Frank, circa 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Memorial services, Ann Arbor, MI, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Concert with Patti Smith, Ann Arbor, MI, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Planet News Tribute in New York City, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Ginsberg Marathon, Ann Waldman, 2001 (Box 3)
  - 50 Years of Howl, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Ginsberg at Tribal Stomp by Greg Savalin, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Tribal Stomp Greek Theatre, Berkeley, 1978 (Box 3)
  - 50 Years of Howl, limited edition (signed by artist), 2006 (Box 3)
  - First Blues LP (signed by Ginsberg and Bob Dylan), 1983 (Box 3)
  - Ginsberg Tribute at Naropa, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tibetan Nyingmapa Benefit, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Promotional Rhino Records, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Concert with Patti Smith (signed by artist), 1996 (Box 3)
  - Memorial Services and Concert (signed by artist), 1997 (Box 3)
  - Beat Rushmore, by Wavy Gravy, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Promotional poster for film The Source, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Reading at the University of Kentucky (signed by Ginsberg), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reading in San Antonio, TX, 1980s (Box 3)
  - Magazine advertisement for GAP khakis, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Reading at Brown University (signed by Ginsberg), 1985 (Box 3)
  - Rogue Dalton Culture Brigade, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Shambhala (signed by Ginsberg), Cambridge, MA, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Naropa Performing Arts Series (signed), 1987 (Box 3)
  - Concert with Bhagavan Das, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Reading at Bryn Mawr, PA, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Naropa with Orlovsky and Scheenmon, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Gathering of the Tribes, second printing, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Various Poets at Tulagi's, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Flaming Youth at Barnard, circa 1974 (Box 3)
  - Naropa with Philip Whalen, circa 1975 (Box 3)
  - Rocky Flats Protest with Orlovesky, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Poetry in Motion with Creeley, 1983 (Box 3)
  - New Blood Reading at Naropa (signed by Ginsberg), 1981 (Box 3)
  - Reading at Rochester Institute (signed by Ginsberg), 1984 (Box 3)
  - Naropa with Corso and Waldman, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Workshop in New York City (signed by Ginsberg), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reading in London, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Reading in Holland (signed by Ginsberg), 1984 (Box 3)
  - Reading in Sweden, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Naropa with Amiri Baraka, circa 1983 (Box 3)
  - Naropa with Orlovsky and Brownstein, circa 1978 (Box 3)
  - Rocky Flats Benefit Arts Festival, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Three lectures (signed by Ginsberg), 1981 (Box 3)
  - Kerouac Conference Historic Readings (signed by Ginsberg), 1982 (Box 3)
  - Kerouac Conference with Kesey (signed by Ginsberg), 1982 (Box 3)
  - The Beat Generation, Fall class, 1982 (Box 3)
  - 108 Images Exhibition in Venice, Italy, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Reality Sandwiches, Nishen, Germany, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Tribute by artist Eric Drowker in New York City, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Mantra Reading with Gary Snyder, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Philip Glass and Allen Ginsberg, 17 November 1989 (Box 5)
  - Undated photograph of Ginsberg and others (Box 5)
  - Song: Fie My Fum, Neurotica, No. 6, 1950 (Box 5)
  - 50 Anniversary of Howl: Naropa University, 25 June 2006 (Box 5)
  - Allen Ginsberg Memorial and Concert program, 25 May 1997 (Box 5)
  - A Memorial Tribute to Allen Ginsberg, 20 April 1997 (Box 5)
  - Yowl (Zippy the Pinhead comic), Bill Griffith, 1996 (Box 5)
- Other Beat Poets and Writers, 1963-2009, (2 boxes) (Box 5)
  - Diane di Prima (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Reading announcement, 16 April 1967 (Box 5)
    - Wedding announcement, 23 June 1972 (Box 5)
    - Mulch, Vol. 3, No. 1, Fall 1974 (8 poems) (Box 5)
    - Formal Birthday Poem-Feb 23, 1964, Poetmeat, No. 6, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Anne Waldman (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Postcards (including a signature), 1994 and undated (Box 5)
    - Pressure, Big Sky, No. 5, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Anselm Hollo (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Some Yak Turds, Doones, Vol. 1, No. 2, undated (signed by Hollo, 2009) (Box 5)
    - Pomology, Tlaloc, No. 11, undated (Box 5)
    - Have A Seat, Not Guilty!, 1975 (signed by Hollo) (Box 5)
    - Gasworks, Winter 1990 (6 poems; signed by Hollo) (Box 5)
    - The Cafe Review, Vol. 6, Spring 1995 (Box 5)
  - Gary Snyder (4 folders, 8 books, 1 oversize folder) (Box 5)
    - Mandala No. 2, Summer 1975. Dutech poetry magazine. (Box 6)
    - Synapse 4, San Francisco Issue, May 1965 (Box 6)
    - New Measure 6: Oxford University, Summer 1967 (Box 6)
    - Kutsu No. 4, Journal of Backcountry Writing, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Kutsu No. 5, Journal of Backcountry Writing, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Kutsu No. 6, Journal of Backcountry Writing, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Zero No. 1., 1978 (Box 6)
    - Northwest Review, Vol. 6 No. 3, Summer 1963. (Signed by Gary Snyder at his contribution.) (Box 6)
    - Northwest Review, Vol. 8 No. 2, Summer 1973. Native American Poetry Issue. (Box 6)
    - Turkey Buzzard Review, July 1977. Includes poems by Gary Snyder's first wife Joanne Kyger and other associates. (Box 6)
    - River Styx 4, 1979. Interview with Gary Snyder by Michael and Jan Castro. (Box 6)
    - Jimmy & Lucy's House of "K", No. 9, January 1989. Poetry from a collaboration of "poets who meditate" at the Green Gulch Zen Garder Center, April 1987. (Box 6)
    - Eastwest Vol. 7 No. 6, June 1977. "The Original Mind of Gary Snyder" interview by Peter Barry Chowka. (Box 6)
    - Eastwest Vol. 7 No. 7, July 1977. "Gary Snyder and the Arte of Writing." (Box 6)
    - Eastwest Vol. 7 No. 8, August 1977. "Gary Snyder on Poetry and Practice." (Box 6)
    - The International Times, No. 28, April 1968. Underground Newspaper from England. (Box 6)
    - The Bloomsbury Review Vol. 27 No. 4, July/August 2007. Interview with Gary Snyder by Trevor Carolan. (Box 6)
    - The American Poetry Review, Vol. 15 No. 6, November/December 1986 (Box 6)
    - Poetry Flash No. 267, April/May 1996 (Box 6)
    - PBA Galleries (San Francisco) catalog. "Fine Literature of the 19th and 20th Centuries with the David Oakley Collection of Gary Snyder." 27 September 2007 (Box 6)
    - Gary Snyder, Japan, 1963. Photo postcard from Travels with Ginsberg. Published by The Allen Ginsberg Trust, 2002 (Box 6)
    - (Gary Snyder) Verses of Heaven and Earth. Postcard advertising a musical event in Oakland, CA with verses from Gary Snyder (Box 6)
    - The Beats in India: A Soul of Asia Symposium. Program from an Asia Society Event, 14 June 2008 (Box 6)
    - Handbill: Reading by Gary Snyder at Trinity Episcopal Cathedral in Portland, Oregon (Box 6)
    - Bookmark with Gary Snyder quote. From a bookstore in Vancouver, B.C. (Box 6)
    - Large poster with photo by Christopher Felver. Naropa Summer Institute, Boulder, Colorado, circa 1980 (Opaperfolder 1, Box 6)
    - Large poster of Gary Snyder playing with a dog, advertising Gary Snyder poetry reading benefit for the Zen Mountain Center, Fillmore Auditorium, 1967. Design by Gompers Saijo. (Box 6)
    - Siberian Outpost broadside, 2010. Signed by Gary Snyder, no. 69/99. (Box 6)